Guide to the Thomas Woolner Letters to John Frederick Lewis
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Thomas Woolner letter to John Frederick Lewis, 1875 January 31; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 10)
  "Jan 31 '75. My dear Lewis, If you refuse being Mr-ed; - I was much delighted with your kind letter and the hope it offered me of a pleasant glimpse of your happy life. Please to ask Mrs Lewis to accept my bow of homage, and say with what pleasure I look forward to making her acquaintance. I know that I have already seen her several times in life, and, if I mistake not, once in her immortality as she looks in the "Bey's Garden," the guardian angel of the richest cluster of flowers, ever glowing and that ever glowed to mortal sight.- Armstead has done a great deal of work for Gilbert Scott, and his chief performance is half the Podium of the Albert Memorial. He has not exhibited much at the R.A. but as they still want two sculptors to make up their traditional number I think they could not have done much better than to elect him. He is brother-in-law of Wells, and is a personal friend of a great many members of the Academy. I do not know what the Authorities will do with Chantrey's gains, but I know that the Prince may praise and the papers may trumpet, but the Academy will not purchase the "Roll Call". - I hate the thought of 3 score years and 10 for some persons, and wish it sometimes to be within the programme of the gods to do as they used in the days of Attica - extend their grace to especial favorites, and give you 20 more years of working vigour. It is to me sad to think that now your genius has reached its highest glory you should be able to do less work than ever and be tantalized with unsatisfied aspirations and unrealized visions of beauty. You will know that one human being feels the loss this is to the world. I think I shall not wait for fine weather, as that may be in the remote future, but as you give permission I shall run down to see you the first clear chance I can see. - My wife cordially reciprocates your kind feelings towards her and sends similar greetings. - Most truly yours, T. Woolner." Marginalia on first page: "The enclosed photograph for Mrs Lewis' Album" (no photograph present). Woolner refers to Calling the Roll after an Engagement, Crimea (better known as The Roll Call ), a painting by Elizabeth Thompson. See: Thomas Woolner, R.A., sculptor and poet, page 303.
  With written place of origin: 29 Welbeck St. W.
  Correspondence; Butler, Elizabeth (Elizabeth Southerden Thompson), 1846-1933. Roll call; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876. In the Bey's Garden; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence; Lewis, Marian, approximately 1826-1906; Armstead, Henry Hugh, 1828-1905
- Thomas Woolner letter to John Frederick Lewis, 1875 March 24; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 11)
  "March 24 '75. My dear Lewis, My wife and I called to see [William] Boxall and found that he had not only pulled through this time but was quite frisky, not on his feet as he never was much that way. He looks better than I have seen him for some time; he seemed pleased when I told him you had made enquiries about him. I saw Dr Quain this morning and he told me that the President was tolerably well, and, for him, quite strong. So that it is satisfactory to know that the East wind cannot kill off all the good folk well up in years. I send this off merely by way of bulletin, as I know it gladdens you to hear of the well being of your old friends.- Ever truly yours, T. Woolner."
  Correspondence; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence; Boxall, William, Sir, 1800-1879; Quain, Richard, 1816-1898
- Thomas Woolner letter to John Frederick Lewis, 1875 May 30; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 12)
  "May 30 1875. My dear Lewis, I hope you are getting better with the bright weather. I came down to spend the day at this lovely place, - the seat of the great Earl Chatham - and having nothing to do but enjoy myself I make a part of that enjoyment saying how-d'ye-do to you. I am truly sorry you do not get strong quickly; and not only on your own account, and on account of art, but also on my own, for I want the pleasure of seeing you. I am Visitor in the Life School till the middle of June; after that is over, I shall turn down to see you if it be only for ten minutes. I do not know what views you have at Walton, but they are sure to [be?] beautiful if you get glimpses of the Thames, but I think they could not beat this Paradisal spot except in the light of the River.- I have not been to the Ex: since it opened, for somehow ordinary work in art seems to me of very little use and gives me no particular pleasure to look at.- Pray make my compliments to kind Mrs Lewis, for she is always kind in telling me of you and I always feel deeply grateful to her.- My wife is here with me drinking in the lovely scenery. Ever truly yours, T. Woolner."
  With printed heading: "Post Town Beckenham"; "Railway & Telegraph Bromley."; "Hayes, Kent."
  Correspondence; Hayes (Bromley, London, England); Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence; Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain)
- Thomas Woolner letter to John Frederick Lewis, 1875 June 21; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 13)
  "June 21, '75. My dear Lewis, It rejoiced my life to see your hand again on paper, and I hope next Friday to behold your veritable countenance, and to hold that hand in my own. It is very good to offer me a bed, but will you smile on my petition? - Instead of staying all night and possibly putting you to some trouble, may I bring my wife to spend the afternoon with you? It will be a joy for her to remember all her life making her bow to you in your own house. There are two convenient trains in the evening, so that all will be comfortable. Alas, alas, my beloved "Lion and Lioness" went. I hated sending it at all; but was forced to send every one of my best to avoid the charge of "merely weeding". I put a reserve of £80, which I hoped would secure its return, but it reached £89. - From the numerous failures in monied circles, and the lateness of the season I was told the sale would be a poor one, and thought my reserve would secure me against purchase, but your renown was too much for my prudence, and I lost my treasure. I intend to lose no more money by bad investments as I did last year and the year before; nothing but jogtrots [?] for the future. Bitter as it was to get rid of my lovely pictures I must say it is a relief to be free from so much responsibility. I will tell you all about everything when we meet. I enclose for Mrs Lewis a pho: of my monument to Bishop [John] Patteson representing him as he lay in the canoe after having been stripped, and a mat thrown over him, and a palm branch with 5 knots placed in his hands.- Ever truly yours, T. Woolner" No photo present. Bishop Patteson was murdered in 1871 in the Solomon Islands; his body was found floating in a canoe, covered with a palm mat and holding a palm branch.
  Correspondence; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876. Lion & lioness; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence; Patteson, John Coleridge, 1827-1871
- Thomas Woolner letter to John Frederick Lewis, 1875 July 18; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 14)
  "July 18 '75. My dear Lewis, I met [Gustave?] Pope at the Mansion House last night and was pained to hear that you were lain up unwell again. I was going to ask if I might run down again before the summer was over to look at your sketches, but now I must wait till you are strong enough again to see anyone. In fact I did not feel sure that a letter would not bother you till Pope said it would rather amuse than otherwise. I cannot tell you the pleasure it is to us to remember the delightful afternoon at your house; we feel as if we had for awhile lived the life of the Arabian Nights, with all its joys and without any of its evil. As generous souls rejoice in the joy they give I am sure that Mrs Lewis and you must have a rich store of enjoyment. I should so much have liked to show you a statue I am doing of Sir Cowasjee Jehangeer, a rich Parsee of Bombay; for while I work at it I think of your work and wonder if you would think I had put the true Oriental character into his attitude and the expression of his face. I should much like to exhibit it next year but my Committee wish it in Bombay before the Prince arrives in November, so that, as usual, I am cheated of my Exhibition right. The President seemed to have revived again last evening, for tho he looked weak compared with a few years back, still he spoke with some amount of firmness and was very pleasant in his manner and cheerful. My wife desires her love to Mrs Lewis and you and is very anxious for comforting news of you. It is this horrid wet weather that has brought you down, for all sensitive nervous natures are more beaten by damp than by any other causes. - Ever truly yours, T. Woolner."
  Correspondence; Orientalism; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence; Pope, G. (Gustave); Jehanghier, Cowasjee Readymoney, 1812-1878
- Thomas Woolner letter to Marian Lewis, 1876 January 16; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 15)
  "Jan 16 '76. My dear Mrs Lewis, the date of your last letter just now shocked me to see how long it was written: it has been on my desk ever since to be answered, and the answer was to be that I meant to jump into a train and to answer for myself. Now, unless I fix a time I shall go on for 3 months longer without paying you a visit, as I never by any chance have a day disengaged, therefore unless you forbid me to do so I shall come to see you on Sunday 23rd. - But if Sunday is a day with you so solemn and lugubrious as to admit of no pleasure to yourselves or anyone else, in Scotch fashion, then I will pick out some other day and learn your opinion upon it, for I intend to go on no longer in this indefinite manner.- I have lots to tell the great Oriental about the fights over the increase of Associates, and long for a wholesome gossip upon Art, men, and things.- Tell him I have to do a Colossal statue of Captain Cook for Sydney, N.S. Wales to commemorate that mighty hero having discovered the place about 100 years ago. I have heard from time to time how he has been going on, and am glad that on the whole he seems to have got on so for thro' the winter pretty well: but considering how long I have allowed you to rest I think you may send me just 2 or 3 lines to say how you are going on.- We have got on very well hitherto. Kindest remembrances from my wife - Ever truly yours, T. Woolner."
  Correspondence; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876; Lewis, Marian, approximately 1826-1906 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence; Cook, James, 1728-1779; Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain)
- Thomas Woolner letter to Marian Lewis, 1876 January 18; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 16)
  "Jan 18 '76. My dear Mrs Lewis, Best thanks; wet or dry I shall come next Sunday at about the time you say. I will tell all about Cook's statue when I come - he is to be on the top of a column so that he must stand - why does the great man wish to see him sitting - he who never rested? Perhaps because he thinks the mighty Captain should rest after so much activity! Ever truly yours, T. Woolner."
  Correspondence; Lewis, Marian, approximately 1826-1906 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence; Cook, James, 1728-1779
- Thomas Woolner letter to John Frederick Lewis, 1876 February 13; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 17)
  "Feb 13 '76. My dear Lewis, I met your brother in the street this morning and was grieved to hear from him that you were not so well and that the cold weather affected you. This cold is most penetrating, for almost ever since I was with you I have been bothered with a cough and irritation in my throat, and I cannot get well in consequence of the cold. If the cold serves me in this unjustifiable manner, my whole life being spent in the exercise of jumping up and down stools and steps, how is it to be wondered at that you are cruelly victimized by the tyrant when you can never take enough exercise to counteract its baneful insinuation. I can tell you nothing of the R.A. transactions at present for as yet nothing has been done. On Tuesday, as you know, there is a General Meeting when the great battle comes off, more Ass:s or "as you was". If anything notable should occur I will be your humble chronicler. I am now obliged to flit and only send this as a nod in passing. - Please to remem. me most kindly to Mrs Lewis, Ever truly yours, T. Woolner."
  Correspondence; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence; Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain)
- Thomas Woolner letter to Marian Lewis, 1876 February 20; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 18)
  "Feb: 20 '76. My dear Mrs Lewis, I ought to have answered your letter before, but of late every evening I have had has been so closely engaged that I have not been my own master but rather the unwilling slave of that unpitying Demon brute - Circumstance. Tho wet a great deal, the weather has been so mild these last few days I hope it has dealt kindly with my well-beloved Patriarch. I was by no means pleased to have your confirmation of what I had heard of him. I am glad you think it does him good to have a chat on the way this queer world wags, and I will run down any Sunday you tell me I may see him without hurting him: my duties of the heavy sort are not yet begun at the R.A. and when they are they will not affect my Sunday, as I rarely work on that quiet restful day. What a joke about a bust of S.C. Hall! - doubtless I have during my life done many things a highly developed - or rather a human creature living in a highly developed civilization ought not to have done; - but I can lay my hand upon my faithful bosom and say "Thank that Destiny, hitherto my guide, I have never yet descended into such a puddle of inanity as to exercise my craft upon the features of Mr Pecksniff!" So pray ask your Husband not on my account to swell the vanity or the pockets of this contemptible sneak.- The R.A. business was very simple last Tuesday - it was decided by a majority of 2 to 1 that a first installment of Associates be elected soon as possible with the vote and all other advantages the present ones enjoy. To my mind this is disastrous because it will stop anything like a large movement towards justice for 25 years or longer, but as it appears to serve the purpose of ambition, and as ambition has a large majority to pedestalize him upwards I suppose the most philosophical thing is to smile at the gregariousness of mankind.- Ever truly yours, T. Woolner." S.C. Hall was the editor of The Art Journal and was renowned for his sanctimonious personality. He was widely considered the basis for Charles Dickens's character, Mr. Pecksniff.
  Correspondence; Lewis, Marian, approximately 1826-1906 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876; Royal Academy of Arts (Great Britain); Hall, S. C. (Samuel Carter), 1800-1889
- Thomas Woolner letter to John Frederick Lewis, 1876 March 9; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (2 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 19)
  "March 9 '76. My dear Lewis, I will be with you on Sunday somewhere about 3 P.M.- and as it will give me more time with you I will stay the night, as I suppose I can get away pretty early in the morning. - I sent your letter to my wife, who is at Hastings; she was charmed with the hopeful tone of it and desired me to give you her love. - I am up and over my head in letters as I have no wife here to carry off the press of them as usual. Ever yours, T. Woolner." Marginalia: "I saw [William] Boxall last night: - he is very feeble I fear.-" William Boxall would die on 6 December 1876.
  Addressed from "29 Welbeck St. W." Addressed to "J.F. Lewis Esq. R.A. Walton-on-Thames"; with postage stamp and multiple postal markings; torn at edges.
  Correspondence; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence; Boxall, William, Sir, 1800-1879; Woolner, Alice, 1845-1912
- Thomas Woolner letter to Marian Lewis, 1876 March 11; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 20)
  "March 11 '76. My dear Mrs Lewis, I am grieved at your sad news, and hope it is only a few days of depression you have to be anxious about. Tell him he must not think of writing unless doing so allows one to accept it as a sign of very great improvement indeed: - mind this is bona fide, and I cannot accede to any vagaries of his generous impulses. I do not at all like writing to my wife that he is worse for his last letter rejoiced her so much; and she gets so little holiday, having this refractory tribe always on her hands, I do not like to send down a cloud to shade her day of sunshine. - She gave in this morning's letter a fine account of the glorious sea and the waves washing over the roadway. The children are with me; so that she has nothing to do but laugh and grow fat. - Hoping for good news- Ever truly yours, T. Woolner."
  Correspondence; Lewis, Marian, approximately 1826-1906 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876; Woolner, Alice, 1845-1912
- Thomas Woolner letter to Marian Lewis, 1876 March 27; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter, signed; 10 x 19 cm, folded to 10 x 10 cm (Box 1, Folder 21)
  "March 27 '76. My dear Mrs Lewis, We were grieved to have your bad news of your glorious veteran; and the weather so abominable that I scarcely expect to have a better yet awhile. Tell him that if I see anything brilliant I will tell him. I am glad he sent his own, for a true blossom is grateful where artificial flowers fatigue. You saw that my wife has returned, and the house has received its soul again. How she longs for cheery news, and to see you both again. Her day at your house is a memory steeped in Romance, for your artist is her ideal of a splendid painter; and I am vain enough to think praise from her of value, as she gives it rarely, and very little of it to me. - I have been too busy to write before - my love to him - every yours, T. Woolner." Marginalia: "Thanks for your kind letters!" See: Thomas Woolner, R.A., sculptor and poet, page 302.
  Addressed from 29 Welbeck Street.
  Correspondence; Lewis, Marian, approximately 1826-1906 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892 -- Correspondence; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892
- Alice Woolner letter to John Frederick Lewis, between 1874 and 1876, January 26; Woolner, Alice, 1845-1912; 1 sheet (2 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Alice Woolner's hand is difficult to decipher. She appears to be writing on behalf of Thomas Woolner to arrange a meeting with J.F. Lewis on January 29th, at the Athenaeum.
  Addressed from 29 Welbeck St.
  Correspondence; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Alice, 1845-1912 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892
- Alice Woolner letter to Marian Lewis, between 1874 and 1876, March 22; Woolner, Alice, 1845-1912; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Woolner appears to inquire about the health of J.F. Lewis, noting "this severe weather I fear is very bad for your invalid."
  Correspondence; Lewis, Marian, approximately 1826-1906 -- Correspondence; Woolner, Alice, 1845-1912 -- Correspondence; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892
- Charles Aitken letter to D. Hewitt, 1914 January 5; Aitken, Charles, 1869-1936; 1 folded sheet (2 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 24 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 24)
  "January 5, 1914. Dear Sir, I am very much obliged to you for your kind letter about the Lewis pictures. I will write to Christies'. I think the Birmingham Gallery must have bought some. I would be very grateful for the addresses of any owners of Lewis's pictures, if it is not troubling you too much. I am yours very truly, Charles Aitken [...]"
  With blind-embossed letterhead: National Gallery, British Art, S.W.; and blind-embossed seal.
  Correspondence; Aitken, Charles, 1869-1936 -- Correspondence; Hewitt, D. -- Correspondence; Birmingham City Museum and Art Gallery; Tate Gallery
- Charles Aitken letter to D. Hewitt, 1914 January 15; Aitken, Charles, 1869-1936; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 24 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 25)
  "January 15, 1914. Dear Mr Hewitt, I am so much indebted to you for your kindness in sending me this valuable list. I want to see Lewis better represented here and shall try to array a little exhibition rather with a view to the Trustees being able to see his work. Mr Horton of Birmingham [i.e., Joseph Horton, d. 1927] has a good big [?] scale one "In the Harem" but he has rather an exaggerated idea of its market price. Sir Cuthbert Quilter had a good one but I do not know at present what became of it. With renewed thanks, I am yours very truly, Charles Aitken."
  With blind-embossed letterhead: National Gallery, British Art, Millbank, S.W.; and blind-embossed seal.
  Correspondence; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876. Harem; Aitken, Charles, 1869-1936 -- Correspondence; Hewitt, D. -- Correspondence; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876; Horton, Joseph, -1927; Quilter, Cuthbert, Sir, 1841-1911; Tate Gallery
- Amy Woolner letter to D. Hewitt, 1914 March 29; Woolner, Amy; 1 folded sheet (2 pages): autograph letter, signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 26)
  "March 29th, 1914. Dear Mr. Hewitt, Thank you very much for searching out the letters of my father and taking so much trouble about the matter. It will be very nice to see you again if you can manage to bring the letters but I should like to know when you mean to come as I might be out - we are leaving this place on Monday April 6th and tomorrow we are out all the afternoon - With our kind regards, I am Sincerely yours, Amy Woolner."
  Addressed from: 106 Queen's Gate, S.W.
  Correspondence; Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892; Woolner, Amy -- Correspondence.; Hewitt, D. -- Correspondence
- Amy Woolner note, 1914 May 19; Woolner, Amy; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph note, signed; 20 x 33 cm, folded to 20 by 13 cm (Box 1, Folder 27)
  A folded sheet of paper, inscribed: "Letters from T. Woolner to J.F. Lewis R.A., returned with thanks & compliments, May 19, 1914, from Amy Woolner, Belle Vue, Chiddingfold, Surrey."
  Lewis, John Frederick, 1804-1876; Woolner, Thomas, 1825-1892